A Guide to the Collections of Lieutenant Colonel Robert W. Rozman and Lieutenant Colonel Thomas R. Rozman, 1864-2012
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Collections of Lieutenant Colonel Robert W. Rozman and Lieutenant Colonel Thomas R. Rozman, 1864-2013
The Library of Virginia
50009
2.55 cu. ft. and 5 boxes
Robert W. Rozman and Thomas R. Rozman
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas R. Rozman of Williamsburg.
Biographical Information
Robert W. Rozman was born 1 April 1920 in Springfield, Massachusetts, to William and Stephania Rozman, one of their twelve children. The family moved to Wilson, Connecticut, where Robert Rozman grew up. Rozman entered the Civilian Conservation Corps in 1939 and then joined the Connecticut National Guard in October 1939. Rozman became a member of Company F, 169th Infantry Regiment, February 1941. He went through military training at Camp Blanding, Florida, and Camp Shelby, Mississippi. Rozman served in the Pacific Theater during World War II, including participation in the Solomon Islands, New Georgia, New Guinea, and Luzon amphibious assault landings. Commissioned a 2nd lieutenant in May 1945, Rozman served in the United States army after the war, rising to the rank of lieutenant colonel, before retiring in December 1965. He returned to Connecticut and operated a successful subcontracting business, retiring from that business in 1987. Rozman moved to Pennsylvania the same year to be near his daughter. Rozman married Candide Gisele Boucher (1924-2008) in April 1946 and they had three children, including Thomas R. Rozman. Rozman died 5 April 2008 in Manheim Township, Pennsylvania, and was buried in Arlington National Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Collections, 1864-2013, of Lieutenant Colonel Robert W. Rozman and Lieutenant Colonel Thomas R. Rozman consisting of photographs of Robert W. Rozman (1920-2008) undergoing military training at Camp Blanding, Florida, and Camp Shelby, Mississippi; in service in the Pacific Theater during World War II; at home on leave; and from his post-war military career. Photographs also include Robert Rozman's wife Candide Boucher Rozman (1924-2008), his son Thomas R. Rozman, members of the Rozman, Boucher and Gagne families serving in the military during and after World War II, as well as photographs of general military training and reviews. Collections include emails from Thomas R. Rozman providing context for the images.
Contents List
- Robert W. Rozman--Civilian Conservation Corps (Connecticut) and Plattsburg Barracks (New York), 1939-1940. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Blanding, Florida, and on leave, Wilson, Connecticut, 1941. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Blanding, Florida, 1941. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Robert W. Rozman--on leave, Wilson, Connecticut, Christmas, 1941. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--169th Infantry Regiment history, colors, and band, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--garrison life, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--garrison life, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--military training, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--military training, tank obstacles, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--military training, river crossing, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--military training--rifle range, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--supply room, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Shelby, Mississippi--visit to New Orleans, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Robert W. Rozman--New Zealand, New Georgia, and New Guinea, 1943-1944. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Robert W. Rozman--map of Pavuvu Island, Russell Islands, the Solomons, 1943. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Robert W. Rozman--2nd lieutenant, 1945. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Robert W. Rozman and Candide Boucher Rozman--wedding and regimental function, 1946, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Edwards, Massachusetts, 1947-1949. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Pickett and Camp A. P. Hill, Virginia (includes Candide Boucher Rozman and Henry W. Rozman), 1951. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Robert W. Rozman--Camp Pickett, Virginia (includes Candide Boucher Rozman and Thomas R. Rozman), 1951. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Robert W. Rozman--deployment, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Robert W. Rozman--deployment and Paris, France, 1951-1952. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Robert W. Rozman--Germany (clippings; includes Joseph F. Boucher, Wildy Boucher), 1952. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Robert W. Rozman--leave, Southern Bavaria, 1953. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Robert W. Rozman--post-Korean War, 1954-1980. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Robert W. Rozman--correspondence, commissions, and certificates, 1943-1965. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Robert W. Rozman--USAEUR United States Army Area Command Commanders Conference, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Robert W. Rozman--service awards from Eastern European Labor Services, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Robert W. Rozman--burial, 7 July 2008. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Carl Rozman, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Earl E. Rozman, 1954-1957. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Elizabeth Rozman (Jansen), 1952-1955. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- George A. Rozman, 1943-1945, 2011. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Henry W. Rozman, 1943, 1951. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Richard W. Rozman, 1954-1956. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Walter P. Rozman, 1948-1969. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Rozman brothers--Walter, George, Henry, Earl, Carl, Richard, and Robert, 1947. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Carl, George A., and Robert W. Rozman at home, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Robert W. Rozman and Richard Rozman--R. W. Maintenance Contractors, 1966-1986. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Thomas R. Rozman, 1951-2011. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Explorer Scout; Cadet at the United States Military Academy, 1962, 1967-1970. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Thomas R. Rozman--1st Platoon, Company A, 2nd Battalion, 12th Cavalry, Fort Hood, Texas, 1971. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Thomas R. Rozman--1st Platoon, Company A, 2nd Battalion, 12th Cavalry in Air Cavalry Command Brigade Test II, Fort Hood, Texas, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Thomas R. Rozman--2nd Battalion, 12th Cavalry change of command, Fort Hood Texas, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company C, 1st Battalion, 12th Cavalry, Fort Hood, Texas, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company B, 1st Battalion, 38th Infantry, Camp Hovey, South Korea, 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Thomas R. Rozman--officers of 1st Battalion, 38th Infantry, Camp Hovey, South Korea, 1972. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company B, 1st Battalion, 38th Infantry, Camp Hovey, South Korea, street scenes, 1972-1973. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Thomas R. Rozman--1st Platoon, Company B, 1st Battalion, 38th Infantry, land navigation course, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Battery D, 2nd Battalion, 44th Air Defense Artillery, Camp Huston, South Korea, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Thomas R. Rozman--aide-de-camp, 2nd Infantry Division, Camp Casey, South Korea, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Brigadier General Thomas U. Greer, Assistant Division Commander for Maneuver, 2nd Infantry Division, Camp Casey, South Korea, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Brigadier General Robert A. Holloman, Assistant Division Commander for Support, 2nd Infantry Division, Camp Casey, South Korea, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Thomas R. Rozman--2nd Infantry Division, Camp Casey, South Korea, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Panmunjom, North Korea, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Yong San Post, United States Army, Seoul, South Korea, 1972-1973. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Thomas R. Rozman--South Korea, 1972-1973. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Republic of Korea Armed Forces Day, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Thomas R. Rozman--3rd Battalion, 7th Infantry, 197th Infantry Brigade, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1974. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company A, 1st Battalion, 58th Mechanized Infantry, Family Day, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company A, 1st Battalion, 58th Mechanized Infantry, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Company A, 1st Battalion, 58th Mechanized Infantry, Mechanized Infantry Fighting Vehicle developmental test, Fort Benning, Georgia, 1976-1978. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Thomas R. Rozman--graduation from the U.S. Army Staff College, 1983. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Thomas R. Rozman--1st Battalion, 46th Mechanized Infantry and 122nd Panzergrenadierbataillon, 1983-1984. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Deputy Chief of Staff for Operations, Armored Family of Vehicles Task Force, 1986-1989. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Thomas R. Rozman--U.S. Army Training and Doctrine Command, Fort Monroe, Virginia, 1992. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Thomas R. Rozman--dedication of Koscuiszko bust, United States Military Academy, 2008. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Thomas R. Rozman--Buque Escuela Cuauhtemoc, 2013. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Thomas R. Rozman--general papers, 1996-2013. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Thomas R. Rozman--bibliography, 2011. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Thomas R. Rozman and Robert L. Rozman--Camp Casey, South Korea, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Robert L. Rozman, 1952-2008. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Bryan T. Rozman, 1992-2013. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Bryan T. Rozman--123rd Support Battalion, 1997. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Melissa Rozman, 1994-2007. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- R. Douglas Rozman, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Raquel Meranda Rozman, 2011-2012. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- David Rozman, 1974-1983. (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Romuald Rosmylowicz, circa 1952. (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Candide Gisele Boucher [Rozman], 1941-1944. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Fernand Boucher, ca. 1930, 1943-1944. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Joseph C. Boucher obituaries, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Lucian Boucher, 1942, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Marie Gagne Boucher, 1943-1944, ca. 1950s. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Roger Boucher, 1942, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Wildy Boucher (including Joseph F. Boucher, Lucian Boucher, Richard Boucher, and James Boucher), 1942-1967. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Boucher family, 1942-1944. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Augustin Gagne, 1864-1865. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Aime Gagne, 1917-1918, 1972. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Alphonse Gagne, 1942-1945. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Alphonse Gagne--with 317th Army Service Forces Band; at home in Connecticut; serving in France and in Germany, 1943-1945 (also includes undated photograph of Gagne's graduating class at the Hart School of Music). (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Alphonse Gagne--with 317th Army Service Forces Band; serving in France, Holland, and Germany, 1943-1945 (includes Emil Couture in one photograph). (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Alphonse Gagne--317th Army Service Forces Band, 1943-1944. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Alphonse Gagne--at gravesite of Aime Gagne, 1945 (includes photograph of Jason Gray at site). (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Arthur Gagne, 1918. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Joseph Gagne, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Jean-Marie Gagne and Jacques Gagne, 1974-1975. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Jacques Gagne, ca. 1974-ca. 1986, 2014. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Jacques Gagne and Joel Gagne, ca. 2003-2004, undated. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Joel Gagne, 2008-2014. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Joel Gagne and Sylvio Bert Berthelette, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Joel Gagne and Michelinne Gagne, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Gagne Family, 1918, 1943-1945. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Ralph and Noella Boucher Barnard, 1941-1943. (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Napoleon Berube, ca. 1920s, 1949. (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Ronald R. Berube, 1950-1965. (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Lucien Bolduc. (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Lucien Bolduc, Jr. (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Eileen Cantin, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Gerry Cantin, 1949. (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Joseph Raymond Cantin, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Maurice Cantin, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Norman Cantin and Cantin Family, 1926, 1943-2011. (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Paul Cantin, 1945, 1962-1967, 2012. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Nelson P. Cheverier, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Nelson Cheverier, 1976-1998. (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Nicholas Cheverier, 2009. (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Ryan Cheverier, 2005. (Box 4, Folder 28)
- William F. Chorazy and Marian A. Rozman Chorazy, 1945, 2003, 2008. (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Emil Couture, 1942-1945. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Emil Couture--with Lorette Boucher Couture, Greg Couture, James Boucher, Wildy Boucher, and Richard Boucher, 1950-2012. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Donald Couture, 1967-1970. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Gregory Couture, 1950-1990s. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Amanda Couture Sill, 2004-2013. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Isidore Couture and Ann Boucher Couture, 1943-1946. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Roger W. Cowles, 1955. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Gayle-Ann Jones Gray, 1967-1973. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Jason Gray, 2006. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Francis Hogan, ca. 1950. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Gregory J. Hogan, ca. 1922-1955. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Larry Hogan, 2008-2010. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Richard Hood, 1943. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Clifford C. Jones, 1944. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Caroline Dayton Kearney, 2003-2011. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Patrick Kenny, -2011. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Leo P. Manter, 1949. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Walter F. Marciniec, 1944-1967. (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Thomas Marciniec, 1984. (Box 5, Folder 19)
- John McGuire, ca. 1944. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Nathalie Kasak McGuire, 1944, 2009. (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Donald Migliuri, 1965-2011. (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Joseph Migliuri, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Francisco A. Raquel, 1940s-1979. (Box 5, Folder 24)
- John Edward Sill, 1998-2012. (Box 5, Folder 25)
- James M. Tanski, 1968-1973. (Box 5, Folder 26)
- John William Tanski, 1962-1991. (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Ken and Tara Viot, ca. 1990s. (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Alexander Voogd, circa 1967-1968. (Box 5, Folder 29)
- 43rd Infantry Division--Camp Pickett, Virginia, 1951. (Box 5, Folder 30)
- 169th Infantry Regiment--Camp Pickett, Virginia, 1951. (Box 5, Folder 31)
- 169th Infantry Regiment--deployment, 1951. (Box 5, Folder 32)
- 169th Infantry Regiment, 43rd Division--Montieth Barracks, Germany, 1952. (Box 5, Folder 33)
- 169th Infantry Regiment, 43rd Division--Montieth Barracks, Germany, 1952. (Box 5, Folder 34)
- National Purple Heart Hall of Fame--Aime Gagne, Joseph B. Gagne, Robert W. Rozman, Henry W. Rozman, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Units of service, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 36)
- General information, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 37)